<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Peace broken, or, Blessings become snares and cursings. By reason of man's disobedience and rebellion.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91543</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871018</idno>
  <idno type="VID">123416</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240944887</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing P919</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E268_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R212395</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871018</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99871018e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91543)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 123416)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 45:E268[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Peace broken, or, Blessings become snares and cursings. By reason of man's disobedience and rebellion.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 46, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in February, 1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first and last leaves are blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Feb: 5th 1644"; the 5 in imprint date is crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="uniform_title">Bible. --  O.T. --  Genesis III, 19 --  Sermons</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:123416:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:123416:1"/>
            <p>PEACE BROKEN, OR, BLESSINGS BECOME <hi>SNARES</hi> and <hi>CVRSINGS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY Reason of Man's Disobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Rebellion.</p>
            <bibl>Mal. 2. 2.</bibl>
            <q>I will curse your Blessings saith the Lord.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in <hi>February,</hi> 1645.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:123416:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:123416:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>GEN. 3. 19.</bibl>
               <q>In the sweat of thy face shalt thou eat thy bread, till thou returne to the earth.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OD Almightie, the great and sole Builder of heaven and earth, in those six dayes, in which his goodnesse did first reconcile the odds betweene being and not being, calling the possible world into act, made these, and but these two natures, the <hi>neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarie</hi> and the <hi>voluntarie;</hi> to the former, as being voyd of reason, and therefore not capable of any positive Law, he gave no precept, hee set Nature to them a rule, and furnisht them with faculties determined, and (if there be no impediment in second causes) necessitated to such or such actions, tending to such or such ends. To the latter, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing endowed with freedome, and a power indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent to both extremes, to doe or not to doe, to doe this or that good or ill, He expressely gave in charge, what (if hee tendered his life) hee should not doe; and therefore hee had no sooner pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced him Lord of the whole earth, but know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how proper it is for happinesse to forget her
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:123416:3"/> selfe, and how safe for Monarchs to remember, that they are dependantly and subordinately great, in the proper tone of a Law-Giver (<hi>Legum enim authoritas ratione suasoria vile est</hi>) tels him flatly, <hi>Of the fruit of the tree which is in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest of the garden, thou shalt not eat:</hi> The tree is now forbidden, and that by the Lord and Maker of it: from henceforth for <hi>Adam</hi> to taste it, shall be disobedience, shall bee intemperance, shall bee injustice; the least of which shall not dwell in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radise, they make too great a stir in the soule, and are too turbulent to reside in him, whom God created as a Citie at unitie in it selfe, there was no insurrection of the sensitive appetite against the will, no deformitie betweene the will and reason, the intellect directed, the will commanded, the members executed: In a word, there was a neat and harmonious consent of all the faculties with reason, and of reason with God; thus was man at peace with God, and with himselfe. But like as from the quietnesse of the aire the Philosopher suspects an earth-quake, mee thinks the man that had not read this book, should have read so much in the book of Nature, tane so much from poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick rules, as to fore-see a declension of things at perfection, to fear most a rebellion in a State most composed: such was the state of <hi>Adam,</hi> and with such successe, in the same day were his affections quiet and tumultuous; his will, which that day had well given up her name, revolted from the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment of reason, judge you how voluntarily
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:123416:3"/> fallen, in that she left her leader, and yet her selfe blind. I ask not whence this desertion, who per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting, who instigating? This is enough for me, this will bring me to my text, if I tell how the evill of sin lets in the evill of paine, and that I find in the sacred History, that our first parents did eat, and this probable in the schoole, that they were both created, both stood, and both fell, and both in one day. Let both these two great lights on earth answer to those two in heaven, and then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the eclipse, that <hi>Hesychius Milesius</hi> speaks of, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The Sun was darkened, and the Moone withdrew her light:</hi> but happy you superiour lights, whose eclipses are not sins, the defects and anomies of humane actions are scann'd at the bar of justice, and bearing a guilt upon the offendent, will not be expiated but by suffering; for let the man but taste of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited fruit, and he shall heare a voyce from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, that voyce which breaketh the Cedars of Libanus, thundring out wrath, and this sad doom, <hi>In the sweat of thy face,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The generals in the text are three: first, the suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferer, <hi>thou;</hi> secondly, his sufferings, <hi>to eat his bread in the sweat of his face;</hi> thirdly, the terme of his sufferings, <hi>till thou returne to the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Since there is so necessary dependancie of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall acts upon intention, it is a good rule which the Phil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>sopher gives in the first of his Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Not to look so much to the letter of the Law, as the mind
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:123416:4"/> of the Law-giver:</hi> The expresse prohibition of eating was to one, but intended for all; one man, our first father did eat, and sin; the sin ran downe to his sons, and to the sons of their sons, and to those that did descend from them, to all nations, sexes, conditions, times, and ages of the world, to the man that shall last see the Sun set. <hi>In the day that thou shalt eat, thou shalt dye the death,</hi> as it sayes more kinds of death than one, so more that should dye than one; <hi>and to dust thou shalt returne,</hi> was more than a personall sentence, for all men were dead in one, and were <hi>gathered to their fathers,</hi> as to a living sepulcher, larger, and more common than that which <hi>Abraham</hi> bought of <hi>Ephron</hi> the son of <hi>Zoar,</hi> which was but for him and for his house; so that it seemes to have a great deale of mind that which the Jewes so talk of, that <hi>Abraham, Isaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> were buried in the same cave with <hi>Adam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if posteritie dyed with him, then it sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with him, and then shall suffer and labour with him; <hi>Sane hoc iniquum videtur</hi> (sayes <hi>Bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus) parentum culpam in liberos derivari:</hi> Does not <hi>Sylla</hi> heare ill for the sonnes of Proscripts? Can a man be guiltie of that which was done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was? Ask the Schoole, Is it not the nature of sinne to bee voluntarie? Does it not require knowledge, counsell, consent, election? If not, why then is not the Wolfe called unjust that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voures the Lamb? Why is not hee cited to <hi>Areo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagus</hi> as well as <hi>Mars?</hi> Why doe not Princes
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:123416:4"/> promulgate their Lawes in the Desarts, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell the affections of the wild Asse to a meane, as well as ours? But <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Arist. Moral. lib.</hi> 3. The Law-giver hath an eye to what is voluntarie and unvolunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie; to the former by the rule of distributive ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice, hee sets out rewards and punishments; to the latter, neither reward nor punishment: How then does God punish the sin of the first man in his posteritie, that personally had done neither good nor ill? How could they conceive, and bring forth sin, who yet themselves were not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, or call it a sin; shall it be a mortall sin? <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Who blames a man for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing borne blind? That does the Judge of the great Court of heaven and earth: and surely the Almightie does not pervert justice, it is not with him as with those Romane Praetors, <hi>Jus dicunt, cum iniqua decernunt:</hi> For like, as by a politicall union, many families become one body civill, so by participation of the same specificall nature, were all men as one man; and like as the acts of any part of the body, as theft, or murder done by the hand, doe not ascribe it to that part, but as it is moved by that first and universall motive principle, the will; so is not that first sin layd to us, as severall persons, but as persons and indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duals meeting in the same universall nature, total<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at once by one man depraved.</p>
            <p>It is not, I confesse, the nature of positive Lawes to bind where they are not known or pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lisht,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:123416:5"/> so that if <hi>Cain</hi> had eaten of the forbidden fruit, <hi>Enoch</hi> his son had not therefore been borne a sinner; but it pleased God, by a peculiar will, to wrap up all men in one <hi>Adam,</hi> whose will should be reputed as the will of all to come, whose inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie should be our innocencie, whose sin our sin, though his repentance not our repentance. Let not dust and ashes wrangle and dispute, how just this is, how much safer is it to rest in his decree, at whose right hand, with the testimony of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, we proclaime that justice sits enthroned, and in the infancie of time did sit, when he examined nature in a true balance, and weighed out to all things their being, their properties, their places, their figures, with most exact conformitie to their exemplarie cause.</p>
            <p>So then you have seene how many came with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the precincts of this prohibition, <hi>Thou shalt not eat,</hi> so many are guiltie of the breach of it, and so many are sufferers. Now I proceed to the suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings: <hi>Democritus</hi> and the Epicure, whether flattering corrupt manners with promise of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punitie, or trembling to joyne wrath with omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potencie, gave out, that God was not angrie at all, but that he sate in Heaven a Dispenser of good things only: The Poet sang of an age that knew not whether <hi>Iove</hi> could thunder or no, and wee have heard of an age, when God as yet had not entered into judgement with the sons of men, when death had no more name, than it hath reall nature, when mans labour was his pleasure, his
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:123416:5"/> life contempl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion, and his dwelling Paradise. But oh <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, The very name of <hi>Troy</hi> is dolefull, how much more of Paradise, it adds to our misery, since we have lost the thing, to keep the name, which at this day sounds no better, than to the Mariner some unhappy place in the sea, famous of old for the notorious wrack of some goodly vessell.</p>
            <p>Well, wee are now unparadised, turned out of our pleasant walks, and must fall to our work, we must <hi>eat our bread in the sweat of our face,</hi> this is our sentence, wherein consider, first the act, eating of bread; secondly, the qualification of this act, <hi>in sweat of thy face.</hi> Man in his innocencie had not a body intrinsecally immortall, but a naturall and elementary body, composed of the same prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples with ours, and using for the reparation of nature food, though not using the very same with us; hee was to eat, though not to eat in sweat: And though he was not (as <hi>Suarez</hi> sayes) in a lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall sense to eat bread, by reason of the toyle in tillage, in sowing, in reaping, in grinding, yet was hee, as the word is meant in my text, to eat bread, it being taken here for all manner of suste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance: and here I cannot passe by that ridiculous conceit of some Rabbins, who from this very word <hi>bread,</hi> doe gather that God condemned all men to jog after the plow, a thing which could not stand either with the nature of man, or with the wisdome of God.</p>
            <p>I declare it thus: The light of nature, a beame
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:123416:6"/> of that intelligible and eternall Son, was not set out by the fall of man, this lighted men out of caves and rocks into societies oeconomicall and politicall: Politicall have for their end <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, selfe-sufficiencie, never to bee found, if all men were plow-men: the multitude of our defects must be supplyed by the multitude and varietie of Arts and Artificials; since then God gave man a naturall appetite of a civill and sociable life, which appetite being naturall, is not in vaine, nor yet was lost by sin; for <hi>Cain,</hi> an hainous sinner, built the first Citie, it had not so well suted either with the nature of man, or with the wisdome and goodnesse of God, to have adjudged all men to that one condition of life; besides, what had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of Sciences, liberall Arts? Had not been mechanicall, rude, and inchoate manners as court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as old <hi>Evander</hi> found them among the wild <hi>Aborigines,</hi> the whole world had been benighted, darknesse had beene on the face of the earth, Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptian darknesse, and yet not felt, and God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe had scarce found an unblemishable Levite to serve at his Altar, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, sayes the 7. of the Politicks, <hi>The Plow-man is no fit Priest.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus much of the act: I now come to the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lification of the act, <hi>In the sweat of the face:</hi> To sweat is proper to the body, yet may be translated to the soule, neither is it a bold metaphore, <hi>Tully</hi> hath it <hi>de Oratore, Commentatio &amp; stylus ille tuus multisudoris est:</hi> so that <hi>Archimedes</hi> sitting still in his study, did sweat as well as <hi>Marcellus</hi> his
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:123416:6"/> Souldiers, then in the middest of Athens, neither does the word <hi>face</hi> restraine the sense to bodily exercise, since it is so frequent by metaphore, to attribute to things incorporeall, things proper to corporeall, thus does <hi>Aristotle</hi> call the understan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <hi>David</hi> prayes, <hi>Turne away thy face from my sins, O God,</hi> when as God hath neither figure nor face.</p>
            <p>Thus much <hi>de signo,</hi> the word, or the name; now <hi>de signato,</hi> or the thing signified: Man is a continuall Actour, the Sun riseth and sets upon his action; waking, he moves, heares, discourses, and when his externall senses are lockt up, his ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getative facultie is at work, and his fansie dreams; the whole man here never rests, nay, let it seeme a paradox, I am sure it is true, there is no rest in Heaven. The grand Stoick denied motion, I deny rest. But yet take this distinction, Rest is either a meere cessation from action, a simple not opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or a cessation from some action that wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried the Agent: there is a great deale of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betweene these two. In the former sense God rested the seventh day, from production of new <hi>species:</hi> In the latter it was not possible for him to rest. In the former, man in all his facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, all at once, is never at rest: In the latter, hee is in the time of sleep, in this sense our God wils neither perpetuall labour nor rest, it was his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence that the Heavens should move, that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers parts of the earth might be disposed by the influence of divers stars; upon this motion fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:123416:7"/> a necessarie vicissitude of day and night, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that a vicissitude of rest and labour: these two God hath wisely knit together, intending the one for the laxation, yet continuance of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The finall cause of rest is labour: Arist. Ethic.</hi> 10. Now penall la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, there is a continuall succession of these two, the end of the one is the beginning of the other; the one is from justice, the other from mercie: Now let <hi>Anaxagoras</hi> look up, and see whether heaven be, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>all of stone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To be, is good; but to be doing, is the good and end of being: wee perfect our selves by acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for the defects of nature are supplyed by ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits, and habits acquired by actions, which so long as they are simply voluntarie, are pleasant, once forced become tedious; so much as they have of constraint, so much of griefe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Rhet. Arist. 1. Violence is beside nature, and therefore hath griefe annexed to it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>These painfull actions which my text cals for, are of the same nature with those that <hi>Aristotle</hi> cals <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, partly voluntary, partly violent; for as the poore man parts with his purse to a thiefe, yet would not doe it, but to save his life, setting the lesse evill in the place of good; so wee spend our spirits in some actions, not because they are plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing to the will, but because they are necessarie, partly to satisfie the Law, partly for the attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, partly for the ornament, partly for the maintenance of happinesse; supposing then that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:123416:7"/> we efficaciously will this end, or happinesse; wee necessarily will these penall actions, as meanes to the end, no other way to be purchased. For our condition is not like that of the Lillies, which are cloathed and spin not; nor that of the little Lambs, whom their mothers bring forth in the mountaines, wrapt in naturall rags against the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries of the aire; neither is it with us, as they say it was with <hi>Mercury,</hi> who was borne in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, found playing on the lute at noone, and dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of oxen at night: wee are first infants, then boyes, then youths; how many are the wants of these ages? and when wee come to be men, wee espy more, and are faine to double our paines, the more our knowledge is, the more intense are our desires, and our desires employ our members; the vast capacitie of our soules, and our large wills adde much to our travaile; the appetite of bruits is terminated here below, our ranges about the earth, the sea, the aire, attempts heaven with waxen wings, mounts up to Angels, to God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, and rests not there; which very unrestinesse, though it be full of anxietie (<hi>Non enim est absque dolore quòd aliquis perfectionem appetat: Aquin.</hi> Comment. on Ethic.) seeme to me wonderfully to exalt man above other creatures, that whereas they al disport themselves in some slender rivulets of good, onely man looks to that boundlesse and bottomlesse deep, the Deitie of his Maker, not to be sounded, not to be compast.</p>
            <p>You have heard the sentence that God hath past
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:123416:8"/> on the sons of men, and that an heavie sentence, yet me thinks easier than if he had condemned us to doe nothing, this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Aristotle</hi> termes it, contradicts not only the nature of the soule, whose verie being is to be, and whose well being is to be well doing, but also the whole nature of things: Could a man stand in <hi>Delph,</hi> which Cosmographers call <hi>Vmbilicum terrae,</hi> the very navell of the earth, and turne his eyes to all positions of place, to the right hand, to the left, behind, before, above, and beneath, hee should find them all meet, and conspire to smother, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose this spurious or supposititious brat, and shall man father it, and harbour it in his bosome?</p>
            <p>Goe to the little Bees, thou sluggard, <hi>Pullos vel triduanos ad pensam vocant,</hi> they set their little ones their task at three dayes old; <hi>nec insenectute in fucos degenerant,</hi> neither turne they Drones in their old ages. Next turne to the Ant, and see her wayes, what are those wayes? Ask the naturall Historian, <hi>Etiam per saxa &amp; silices vestigia vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deas &amp; semitas,</hi> Thou mayest find her steps and paths upon the hardest flints: So often does that little, yet exemplary creature, trudge this way and that way, backward and forward, to store her earthy granarie, and keep off a winter fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine.</p>
            <p>Now if there be any to whom God hath dealt so liberall a portion of these temporall goods, as that they need not labour to prevent either want or cold, or famine, even to these also do I preach,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:123416:8"/>
               <hi>In the sweat of thy face shalt thou eate thy bread:</hi> they that sit on high, so high, that the poor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low seeme <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, no bigger than Ants, sayes <hi>Lucian,</hi> are not alway to sit still, qualitie and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition exempt not from labour, but from the manner of labour; and therefore does <hi>Solomon</hi> set the Spider, that embleme of industrie, in that she spins her Web out of her owne bowells, to spin even in the Courts of Princes, though she has beene often swept out for her labour. Why now should the sluggard yet fold his armes? why should he for fortie, fiftie, sixtie yeares rest those bones to whom nature owes so long a rest? surely his soule is crept into his bodie to the same end that <hi>Epimenides</hi> did into his Den, to sleepe out sixty yeares: he forgets how long a rest he is like to take in the grave, hee and all the travellers of the earth; let the poore labouring man, he that grinds in the Mill, the hireling, whose paines are trebled by the sins of great ones, solace him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe with this, that this day shall end in a night, not like the nights of the yeare, which after a few houres give place to the day: nor like that in <hi>Ogy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> his time, famous for nine monthes, but lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and more shadie: where <hi>Abel</hi> has slept al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most from the foundation of the world, where <hi>Israel</hi> makes not, nor Aegyptian <hi>Pharaohs</hi> tire the people with building Pyramids, where silent Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions sleep in beds of Clay, and shall not rise, nor wake, nor rub their eyes, till the Trumpet shall sound in their eares, and heaven and earth infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:123416:9"/> shall light them new start up to Christs Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunall.</p>
            <p>Thus much of our sufferings: the terme of suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering followes in these words, <hi>Till thou returne to the earth:</hi> where you may take notice of foure things: the first implyed our comming from the earth: the second exprest our returne to the earth: First, as the end of evills: Secondly as it selfe an evill. First of the part implyed, our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming from the earth. <hi>Luc. Iun. Brutus</hi> consulting with the Oracle, who should be Consull, received this answer, <hi>That he should be Consull that first kis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed his mother,</hi> he by and by fell on his face, kis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed the earth, returned home, and was created Consull, <hi>Romes</hi> first Consull: beside the faith of the Historie, that man is of the earth, witnesse the like qualities of his nutriment, his sinking in the water, melancholy, his compact flesh, the drynesse of his bones, the constancy of his figure, and that which is not of least moment, the base worldling, that has fixt his eyes on the earth, and by his life-preaching Gentilisme, does sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice at <hi>Vesta's</hi> Altars, and calls her the mother of gods and men; it may be <hi>Lucretius</hi> read his Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digree, where hee tells of men, whom the earth after certaine conversions of the heaven growne big, brought forth and nursed with her owne milke: But let the Poet dreame of prodigious birthes, we know <hi>that God made man of the earth,</hi> I doe not say as some did, fetcht from the foure extremities of the earth, to shew that his Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:123416:9"/> and the world had the same bounds, but of earth: First, that wee might the more joy in our Ascension to heaven, and glorifie our Maker, for raising our heavie bodies to so high a place above the Ayre, above the Fire, above the Moon, and though <hi>Leucippus</hi> taught <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that the Orb of the Sunne was the supreame Orb, above the Sunne, above all the Starres, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept those that praysed him in the morning. <hi>Iob.</hi> 38. The blessed Angels, whose early harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny eccho'd to the harmony of the new borne world.</p>
            <p>Secondly, of earth, that we might have from whence to raise our soules: but not why to raise our Crests, that great ones might not look too big on the poore, but resemble in this that glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Planet, the bright eye of the World, the Sun: the higher it is, the lesse it looks, that they might consider, the humble shrub lives in Mount <hi>Leba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non,</hi> as well as the stately Cedar, and many times lives longer, alway safer: that 'tis somecimes in States as in nature, that gives to lighter bodies the higher place; that all faces are drawn in dust, though some in illustrious dust; that very <hi>Cyrus,</hi> who in his time was writ <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, now begs his memorie as <hi>Strabo</hi> writes, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, O man I am <hi>Cyrus,</hi> he that stiled him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe great from the Empire of the earth, stood but like the Embleme of inconstancie, with his foot upon a Globe, a slippery Globe, earth upon earth: he and poor <hi>Diogenes</hi> lived both but for a
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:123416:10"/> time, and both in a time, though not both in a Tub: and <hi>Plutarch</hi> sayes, they dyed both in one day: Death you see makes no difference, and Christ himselfe seemes to make none: 'tis noted to this purpose, that on the mount there appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with him <hi>Moses</hi> and <hi>Elias,</hi> the one in his younger yeares was a mightie man in Aegypt, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a leader of Gods people: the other, alway poore, cold, and hungrie, cloathed with Goats haire. Away then with that Knave <hi>Lisippus,</hi> that must needs paint <hi>Alexander</hi> with a Thunder-bolt in his hand, with <hi>Caligula,</hi> that set his head on <hi>Jupiters</hi> shoulders, and with <hi>Darius,</hi> that by all meanes must bee a god, though but for thirtie dayes: better was that speculation of <hi>Philip</hi> the <hi>Macedonian,</hi> who on a time falling, and view<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the dust his length, cryed out, <hi>Lord what a little portion of earth is not content with the whole earth:</hi> he well took notice, that as he had falne on the earth, so hee came from the earth: which is my first part; and should returne to the earth, which is my second.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Rhet. 2. Arist.</hi> who knowes not that he shall dye? to consult about an escape were <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously to deliberate what course a man might take, that the Sun should not rise or set. I have read of Temples dedicated to Feares, but that no peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple did ever consecrate a Priest or Temple to death, as being well knowne to bee inexorable; who have not heard of the gates of Death? who
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:123416:10"/> knowes not that they lye open, and that for him? yet because Evills that may bee farre off doe not much affect: and wee while the bloud runs hot in our veines put farre from us, that frozen and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numbed age, as if eternall <hi>Hebe</hi> or Youth fild our Cups, as Poets say shee does their <hi>Joves:</hi> it will not be out of place or time, in the middle of Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer to admonish of Winter; 'twas the Devills policy in old time, to have the dead buried with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Walls, out of sight, that the living might not lay it to heart: he that steeres well, must sit at the end of his Boat: and 'tis the good Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tician, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, when danger is farre off, then to suppse it neare: in this respect it cannot bee out of season: this is my second part, our returne to the earth.</p>
            <p>The whole man came not from earth, and therefore cannot returne to the earth: the soule shall goe to places deputed to her, the body to the earth, one and the same our Mother, our Nurse, our House, our Tombe; that these two should part, proceeds from causes Morall, and Naturall; the Morall cause is sinne, that made a separation of God from the soule, then follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a separation of the soule from the body: for God made not Death, neither taketh the Pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter pleasure in bruising an earthen Pitcher: two things (I may safely say) cannot God make, a God and Sin; of these (take the word properly, he has no <hi>Idea.</hi>)</p>
            <p>The Naturall causes of Death are either
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:123416:11"/> externall or internall; externall, O that I could number them! I should then learne to number my dayes: the internall cause is the mutuall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict of contrarie qualities: the brain being cold, the Stomack, and the Liver hot, the Bones drie, and the Reines moyst: the soule comes from the Father of Spirits, it selfe a Spirit; into a body whose principles exercise naturall and irreconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able enmitie: me thinks at her first entrance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an house so divided against it selfe, she should looke about her like that fellow in <hi>Libanius,</hi> that comming home, and finding painted on his Wall two ready and instructed Armies, cries out, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; who has made my house a Military Campe? The members of every mans body are at continuall Warre; wee may bee at peace with forraine enemies, our domestick are alway in armes: 'Tis false that <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linus</hi> writes of a people in <hi>Iurie,</hi> that are so e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually mixt, their temper so arithmeticall, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out excesse, defect, or jarre, <hi>ut aeterna gens sit ces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>santibus puer periis,</hi> that there is alway the same number of people, and yet no children borne: Who shall make me believe that <hi>Iurie,</hi> or any part of <hi>Jurie</hi> is exempted from death, since life it selfe, our Lord and Saviour Jesus did dye in <hi>Jurie?</hi> Death erects her Trophies as well in <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> as <hi>Greece,</hi> and in <hi>Greece</hi> as <hi>Scythia;</hi> her victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries are here above, her Captives lie below; God made the face of the earth to bee inhabited, sin and death the bowells: this is the place of them
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:123416:11"/> that live, that of them that have lived. Thus is the earth the common receptacle of the living and of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he dead: other Elements serve us in our life, her service continues after death, when our funerall fires have turn'd us to ashes, when the Aire our Breath hath left us, and the water belcht us up, shee is to our tossed bodies a shore, to our bodies turn'd to ashes an Urne, to our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies out of breath a place of Repose, a Seat to rest in.</p>
            <p>Thus much of my second part, our returne to the earth: I now come to our returne as the end of evills. <hi>Hercules</hi> his Pillars were the terme of his Travailes, the terme of his life was the terme of his labours; Life and Labour goe hand in hand, death and rest: hence some did conclude it the prime good not to be borne, the next to dye speedily: <hi>Plinie</hi> thought so well of death, that he conceived no other end of venemous Herbes, than to rid men out of life, <hi>siquando taedio esset,</hi> when it grew wearisome. But <hi>seek not,</hi> said <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon, death in the errour of your lives;</hi> Death is not to bee hastened, and need not bee feared: never did Pinace arrive at the blessed Islands, that first passed not through the straights of Death; God and Nature have set them between us and home.</p>
            <p>There is a place, sayes <hi>Iob,</hi> meaning the grave, where there is no order; and yet this for our comfort, there is no tumultuous confusion, for <hi>Pompey</hi> and <hi>Caesar</hi> are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t peace, the Senate and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:123416:12"/> the people, nay <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Carthage:</hi> Fortune there rules no Orbe, anger and revenge lye chai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned up, and they that divide the Empire of our living world, pride, ambition, injustice, fraud, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetousnesse, oppression, have not so much as one little Province: 'Twas well done of Nature, that condemned us not to any long stay here, that cuts off our sins with our thred, and our paines with our lives, for did not men weep oftner be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the floud than after? and did not old <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amus</hi> shed more teares than young <hi>Troilus?</hi> to all that float upon the troubled waves of this world, there is one common and universall Haven, the haven of death, and yet even there in the very haven doe all men suffer ship wrack, which casts me on my fourth and last part, the discourse on death, as death is an evill.</p>
            <p>Sin, and the punishment of sin, are members adequally dividing humane evils; the former pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>supposed no evill or privation, it presupposed im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection in him that sinned, as mutabilitie of will, which is no evill or privation; for it is uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versally &amp; actually in all individuals; but no priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is actually affirmed of the whole <hi>species:</hi> the later presupposed evill, an inordination in free a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions or omissions, called <hi>Malum culpae,</hi> which in Gods justice is payed with that other, called <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum poenae,</hi> the evill of punishment, to which mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber I reduce the hate of Nature, the last enemy, the last of evils, Death; but not the least.</p>
            <p>Can that be the least of evils, which is so abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:123416:12"/> of all those appetites which God hath printed in the soule, to wit, the naturall, animall, and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall? Does not the nutritive facultie earnestly labour to maintaine us in being, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, sayes <hi>Aristotle, Mor.</hi> 1. even when wee are asleep? Does not the irascible defend our being, and the concupiscible, together with the generative pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagate it? Does not that universall facultie (as <hi>Suarez</hi> cals it) the will, love and desire, the being and well being of all inferiour parts? Shew mee but any thing of the most obscure being, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires not to maintaine that being, and I shall the sooner with the Egyptians believe two Gods that made the nature of things, the one good, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bad. Stay then, take notice, see and be ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed too, to see by what strange wayes and win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings the derived rivers become tributarie to the sea, all things flow from the deep of divine good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, see how hee fetches them back againe, hee hath made them all, at least by some analogie, to love him in that they love themselves; for they are drops of the bucket, and so much as they love themselves, which are by participation, so much they must needs love him, which is of himselfe; they cannot love to bee, but they must love him who swallowes up in his infinitenesse of being, all being, whose nature and essence it is to be, let me tell you of a paradox, if there bee any in afflicted <hi>Jobs</hi> case, that weep that they died not from the womb, that blesse the barren mother, and the paps that never gave suck, even these, the damned spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:123416:13"/> and unhappie soules, out of a meere love to their being, desire not to be: such is our love to our being, and God himselfe glories to say of himselfe, <hi>I am,</hi> and yet this our being does death, as far as it can, destroy.</p>
            <p>Againe, can that bee the least of evils, which drownes in teares the eyes of widdowes and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phans? that leaves the streets as a green field, and changes the palaces of Princes into lodges of Bars and Owles, that had not God for a father, nor Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for a mother, till she was adulterate? that is ushered in by a thousand evils, the sword, pesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and famine, excesse in labour, excesse in plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, lingring; griefe, and sudden mirth, with a thousand more.</p>
            <p>Now that death is a passage from these to a more blessed mansion, from these cloudy regions to those enlightned by the Lord God, it is no thank to death, death is still the ruine of Nature, the demolisher of Gods Worke, this is the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and power of God, who will raise us againe out of the dust, and the dark grave, and then will blesse us, and shew us the light of his countenance, and say in the end of the world as hee said in the beginning, let there be light, and there shall bee light; a light that no Cloud from thenceforth shall dim, that shall never set: to which light hee lighten us, who lighteth every man; nay who is that very light, and for Iesus Christ his sake, our onely Lord and Saviour. </p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:123416:13"/>
            <head>The second Sermon.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>ECCLES. 12. 1.</bibl>
               <q>Remember now thy Creatour in the dayes of thy youth.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Text naturally falls into these parts: First, an act, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member:</hi> Secondly, the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of that act; and that first in a generall notion, as the <hi>Creatour:</hi> Secondly, in a spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall, with this restraint or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriation, <hi>thy Creatour:</hi> Thirdly, the time when, set forth three wayes: First, <hi>in thy youth:</hi> Secondly, <hi>in the dayes of thy youth:</hi> Thirdly, <hi>now in the dayes of thy youth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>First, of the act, <hi>Remember:</hi> But because the memorie of any thing does of necessitie suppose the former knowledge of that, here comes in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other act, layd downe by way of supposition, that we know God: First then of this supposed; <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premum in homine</hi> (sayes <hi>S. August. de Civit. D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i) attingit supremum in mundo;</hi> The noblest faculty
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:123416:14"/> in the little world, man, reacheth to the noblest thing in the great world, God, the builder of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth. When God in the creation did stamp on the rude <hi>Chaos</hi> this face of method, hee was not lavish of his owne image, he gave to hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane nature an intellectuall soule, and became himselfe the object of it: Hee hath not dealt so with everie nation, goe downe into the deep, and tell me if that scaly people have heard of the God of Hosts. Doe they that dwell in the aire, those winged Tribes, sing Psalmes to him that taught them, to him that made them? Doe the beasts of the forrest build him a Tabernacle? or the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dars of Lebanon religiously bow their heads to him? No: they are not capable of so royall ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, their portion is not fallen in so faire a place, they all move in shallower waters; only man, like the stately Pine, lanches out into the Maine, and moves upon that boundlesse and bottomelesse Ocean, the infinite and invisible God.</p>
            <p>Now the knowledge of this God is two-fold, either revealed by Oracles, visions, dreames, tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, Scripture, divided into the new or old Canon; or naturall, such as the Heathen and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles had by the bare light of reason, which though compared to ours, it was no more than the Glow-worme to the Sun, yet was enough to leave them inexcusable, if according to that measure of knowledge, they did not honour the true God.</p>
            <p>The meanes by which they came to this know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, was first by reflection on their owne soules.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:123416:14"/>
            <p>Secondly, by the unsatiable appetite of happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, which cannot rest in any finite good.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, by the powerfull conservation and upholding of all things: and here, O Lord, to whom shall I liken thee, either in heaven, or in earth? What Agent, either naturall or artificiall, is such to his effect, as thou to the world? What the Sun produced by day, it leaves at night, and Arts, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, sayes <hi>Aristotle, Lib. 1. Mor. cap.</hi> 11. though they are fond of their owne works, and love them as their children, yet leave them to strangers, to fortune, to rust, to time. Where is <hi>Minerva,</hi> the work and glorie of <hi>Phidias?</hi> or <hi>Mercury,</hi> of <hi>Polycletus?</hi> Time hath razed their Temples, and like <hi>Metellus,</hi> when he took <hi>Athens,</hi> hath cursed the verie Gods in triumph. But of all the works of God, of all the parts of this great whole, there is not one mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing, not one growne feeble with time, or that stoops to age. I have seene the heavens painted on <hi>Atlas</hi> his shoulders, but me thought he made a filthy sowre face. There is one, and but one, sufficient for this, hee that cast the mountaines in their mold, and weighed them in a ballance, hee that stretcht forth the heavens as a curtaine, and spread them like a tent to dwell in.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, by the neat linking of causes with themselves, and with their effects, by the voyce of the heavens; for their sound is gone out into all lands, since their creation have they both day and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:123416:15"/> night preacht their Creatour, <hi>Non verborum, sed rerum eloquentiâ,</hi> sayes the Father, <hi>Not with elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of words, but of things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Lastly, in this great volume of Nature, what page soever they turned, they might (as in a faire print) read a God. So that to them that never saw the books of <hi>Moses,</hi> as Pagans and Heathens, who never read that in the beginning, God crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the heaven and the earth, it will be damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on not to know a God. For like as though God had never said, <hi>Thou shalt not kill,</hi> or, <hi>Thou shalt not steale,</hi> it had beene sin to take that whcih is not a mans owne, or to shed mans bloud, because the voyce of Nature cries loud against it (and therefore was <hi>Cain</hi> guiltie of murther, before the Law was given in <hi>Sinai</hi> against murther.) So though God had never revealed himselfe, yet not to have knowne him, had beene inexcusable igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, usually called in the Schoole, <hi>Ignorantia vincibilis, Ignorantia pravae dispositionis, Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantia privativa:</hi> that is, the absence of that knowledge, which though we have not, yet wee might, and ought to have had.</p>
            <p>But in us there can bee no such ignorance, the night is past, and darknesse is no more upon the face of the earth, we all know him, wee speake of him, wee sing of him, wee confesse him with our pens, our words, our prayers, and daily oathes, when wee are but in our cradles, wee are taught to call God Father, and while wee hang on our
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:123416:15"/> mothers breasts, to say, <hi>I beleeve in God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But because to know God, and proceed no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is like <hi>Moses</hi> from Mount <hi>Nebo,</hi> to have a view of the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> but to dye before he could set foot in it, because we know God as wee are men, but remember him as we are good men: therefore I now proceed from the supposed act, the knowledge of God, to that other explicite act, the remembrance of him.</p>
            <p>The good actions of men are of small continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and cease to be so soone as their effect is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat, like as naturall motion ceaseth when the forme is produced. If they continue for any time, they may thank the memorie of posteritie, that faithfully records the noble acts of her fathers, &amp; suffers not the same dust that covers their bodies, to cover their names; by her they that dwell in the dust live, and the bodies of Martyrs shall bleed a fresh to all generations; it is she that writes good deeds with a pen of iron, and makes the acts of one age the historie and lecture of the next.</p>
            <p>Now in this respect doe men call for a <hi>remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> that seeing they themselves have no long parts to act upon the stage of this world, when the time comes they must goe out, the curtaine be drawne, and they put off their upper clothes, their bodies, they may leave to this world their name behind them, to testifie that they themselves had sometime beene here: but in this respect cannot God require our remembrance of him, seeing that
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:123416:16"/> what he is, hee hath beene from all eternitie, and so shall continue, when time shall bee no more. The reason why hee cals for our remembrance of him, is not any benefit that shall accrew to him; alas, how far is a creature, a silly man, a little quickened dust, from adding to him, who if hee himselfe could adde any thing to himselfe, I would not acknowledge him my God; the fulnesse of his perfection excludes all accesse of new, our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, our psalmes, our remembrance of him doe him no good, <hi>Quòd colitur Deus, homini prodest, non Deo: neque enim fonti quispiam dixerit se pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuisse si biberit, nec soli, si viderit:</hi> If we do God service, wee profit our selves, not God; for who will say, that the fountaine is beholden to him that quenches his thirst at it; or the Sun to him that sees by it. There is a service, whose end is onely the benefit of him that rules, and this is more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly called servitude; and it was the lot of that impious son of <hi>Noah, Cursed is Cham, a servant of servants shall he be.</hi> Again, there is a service where the benefit is partly his that rules, and partly his that is ruled, and such a service had hee in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spell, in whose behalfe the Centurion besought Jesus in this forme, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Lord, my boy lyes at home sick of a palsie:</hi> And the Originall will beare, <hi>my child lyes at home sick of a palsie.</hi> And such a service was that wee read of in Genesis, and <hi>Isaac</hi> blessed <hi>Esau,</hi> that he might serve his brother. But now beyond both
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:123416:16"/> these, there is a relation of Lord and Servant, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene God and Man, where the Lord reserves to himselfe onely honour, and puts over all the profit to us his servants; and yet though our ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice be not good to him, but to our selves, it is his pleasure and goodnesse to require it; it is he that led the pen of <hi>Salomon,</hi> when he began this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as wee should begin every day of the weeke, every day in the yeare, <hi>Remember now thy Creator in the dayes of thy youth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Creator is the object of our remembrance, and that first in this generall notion, as the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor: secondly in a speciall as thy Creator: First of the generall; the poore Philosopher that knew no other, no better God than the Sunne, when he was asked for what he was borne, made an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to looke upon the Sun; though his ignorance was too too grosse, in that he made a God of a Creature, adoring the Sun for him that inflamed the Sunne; yet had his ground beene true, had that beene a God which he supposed to be a god, how worthy had his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer beene, to be sent in Letters of gold to po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steritie, to read and practise: bee it what it will, 'tis writ against us, and shall be read against us at the great accounts, if knowing the true God, we denie him in our lives.</p>
            <p>Of all those Acts by which Almighty God communicates himselfe to the Creature, hee is most visible in his act of Creation, as for his
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:123416:17"/> acts of executive providence, though they are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually certaine, yet they are not equally seene: it was the ignorance of those that puzled the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picure, and drove him to his wits end, to finde out, why all things come alike to all, to him that sacrificeth, and to him that sacrificeth not, why the thunder-bolt should passe a Taverne and fire a Temple; why the Foxes should have holes, and the Birds of the aire nests, but humility and simplicity not where to lay their head: which knot when he had thus tyed, but could not untie, hee desperately broke it, and peremptorily sets downe, that there was a God in heaven: but he, a carelesse and sleepy one, wherein in that he took away from him providence, hee indeed left him no God: not much unlike the <hi>Cretians,</hi> that call their god <hi>Iove</hi> immortall, yet talke of his Tomb with this inscription, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Here lies <hi>Iove</hi> the Son of <hi>Saturne;</hi> but his act of Creation, he that sees it not must needs be guiltie of damnable ignorance, of voluntarie and affected ignorance, and seems to have his eye-lids given him for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing else but to shut out day; and therefore this remembrance of God is rather urged from his act of Creation, than from his act of Providence.</p>
            <p>There is a second reas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n which may claime our remembrance of him, and that is the extent of his goodnesse in this act of Creation; before heaven or earth, before day or night had God beene of eternall, and infinite continuance, he was
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:123416:17"/> then alone, solitarie, yet wanted no company: it is not with him, as with man, whose naturall infirmities breed a naturall, and necessary desire of society: hence says <hi>Solomon,</hi> two are better than one, neither wanted he the earth for a foot-stoole: to want a foot-stoole is proper to bodies, to ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary and grosse bodies; neither wanted hee a house do dwell in, for then he should want it now: For behold the heaven of heavens con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines him not: and yet for all this it pleased him to create an heaven and earth, the one for thy Footstoole, the other for thy Canopy, both of them of rare beauty, of wonderfull continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, of such perfection, that to them, as <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> sayes, no man can add, and from them can no man diminish, unlesse it be some one so wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly curious, as he is <hi>Lucian,</hi> that blamed him first for making a woman: secondly, for placing the Bulls hornes above his eyes.</p>
            <p>But because no efficient acts at randome, but has respect to some end which either it selfe tends to, but apprehends not, as it is in all things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low man, or which it selfe both tends to and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends, as it is in all intellectuall agents, and chiefely in the first, the infinite wise God; who therefore in the Theologie of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the first intelligence: take further notice of the end for which hee became a Creator, and then unlesse thou be more stupid than <hi>Clusius Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binus,</hi> that could never hit of <hi>Hectors</hi> Name, or
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:123416:18"/>
               <hi>Messala Corvinus</hi> that forgot his owne, thou canst not but with thanks and amazement call to mind thy God, thy Creator, and his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies which have beene of old. Look into the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and nether world, both Sunne and Moone give thee to see, though they see not themselves and in this lower world, whatsoever bleats or lowes, or roares upon a thousand hills, whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nts in the aire, or is silent in the water, both are, and grow, and multiply either for thy pleasure or for thy necessitie: descend from the sensitive degree to the vegetative, thou shalt find the Laurell in the cold of Winter put off her leaves for <hi>Caesars</hi> head: for him the Pine leaves her native Mountaine, for an inhospitall Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and at the Artificers pleasure the Cedar comes downe from Lebanon, and puts on the forme of men, of beasts, of gods. If this bee not enough, doe but thinke how GOD hath placed the head of trees below the foot of man, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, The head of a tree is the root. <hi>Arist. de anim.</hi> Of all these, <hi>Et Dominiū &amp; usus fundatur in humana natura, Suar. de oper. 6. dierum, Both Dominion and use is founded in the nature of Man:</hi> Whatsoever hee created in those first sixe dayes of the world, hee made in reference to thee; to thee (I say) whosoever thou art; he desires no man to remember him for whom hee did not create these things: hee that hath not so much land as hee can cover with his
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:123416:18"/> prostrate body, for him was the whole earth crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: whatsoever is now inclosed, had not sin en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the world, should have laine common: the Civilian had not broacht those termes of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vision, dominion, acquisition, prescription, usu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caption, occupation, it had not beene in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troversie whether the Mariner might cast An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor at this or that shore, nor whose was the swarme of Bees that setled in this or that tree, there had beene no setling of Land-marks, no buying, no selling either of hand of Iustice; no Michaelmas or Easter Terme. <hi>Aquinas</hi> notes, that buying or selling was never heard of, till <hi>Abraham</hi> bought a burying place of <hi>Ephron</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Zoar;</hi> and here by the way you may note, that the first thing this good man bought was a burying place, as if the end of his life had beene the beginning of his thoughts: the River of God, sayes the <hi>Psalmist,</hi> is full of Water; you have heard how this River keepes not within bancks, but rejoyces to break out, and runne downe with a mightie streame, to make glad the face of the whole earth.</p>
            <p>Thus much of the object in generall, as the Creator: I now come to the object in a more spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall notion, with this restraint or appropriation, <hi>thy Creator:</hi> where wast thou when I laid the foundation of the earth, (saies God to <hi>Iob</hi>) let the Poet make answer, <hi>quâ non nata jacent,</hi> were things that are not yet borne or conceived are,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:123416:19"/> that is just no where: how much then dost thou owe to God that gave thee life, when as yet thou couldst not aske it of him? and when hee first gave thee life, thou wast as thy dayes are, but a span long, and yet what a faire place did he make ready for thee? even the wide and spacious world, that when thou commest to yeares and mans sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, thou mightest have elbow roome enough.</p>
            <p>That God is the Creator, and therefore Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, is matter of feare and trembling; but that he is thy Creator is matter of love, and thankfull remembrance. Did he not give thee a being? yes, but so he did to stocks and stones. Did hee not give thee a soule and life? thus much hee hath done for beasts and trees. But did hee not give thee a reasonable soule? to denie it were the best argument, that hee did not. But in that hee hath given thee a reasonable soule, remember this thing that he hath done for thee: The soule of Beasts is from the earth, earthly; the soule of man from the Father of Spirits, and is spirituall; the soule of Beasts is but for a time, and then dyes with the body, the soule of man lives after the body, and returnes to God that gave it.</p>
            <p>Some of the old Philosophers compare the soule of a man to a Circle; for like as a Circle returnes to the first poynt, and ends where it began, so the soule of man returnes to God from whom it began: to which may that bee well ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed which God sayes of himselfe, <hi>I am the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:123416:19"/> beginning, and I am the end.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now though it bee true that the wise men said of old, that the soule of man doth resemble a circle; yet is there some disparitie and unlikenesse in the one and the other; for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Circle returnes to the poynt from whence it begins, but every mans soule doth not returne to God that gave it: for the souls of the wicked go out from him, and are lost in this world, and never returne to him againe: but the soules of the just are like the Dove which <hi>Noah</hi> sent out of the Arke, which finding no rest for the sole of her foot, returned back againe, and hee put forth his hand and received her. In this doe the soules of good and bad agree, that they were all created by one and the same God, that they are all for a time to be united to the body, that they shall all at the end of that time be separated from the body, that they shall all put on the very same bodies which sometimes they put off; that they shall all come to judgement; and here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnes the woefull and lamentable difference, some proving Chaffe, some Wheat; some Sheep, some Goats; some being set on the right hand, and some on the left; some marked out to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall death, and some to eternall life: now that thou maist never feele the happinesse of the one, and never feele the miserie of the other, take with thee this Counsell, it is the Counsell of a King, of <hi>Solomon</hi> the King, let it bee to thee as the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:123416:20"/> Signet of thy right hand, and as Jewells of gold about thy neck; write it upon the Nayles of thy fingers, upon the palmes of thine hands, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the posts of thine house, and in every corner of thy heart, <hi>Remember thy Creator.</hi> The fruit that will spring from this remembrance, will be much and rare: from contemplation of his high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and thy low estate will spring humilitie, from thought of this, that hee gave to thee not onely when thou hadst nothing, but wast no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, Charitie to the poore, from his mercie hope, from his Iustice a true ballance; feare of his Name, resolution and contempt of injuries, from his immensitie and illimited presence in all places, watchfulnesse and warinesse in all thy ways, words, and actions.</p>
            <p>But because there is an appoynted time for all things, a time for everie purpose under the Sun, my Text does not only set downe whom we must remember, but the time when we must remember him, and that in three particulars:</p>
            <list>
               <item>First, in our youth.</item>
               <item>Secondly, in the dayes of our youth.</item>
               <item>Thirdly, now in the dayes of our youth,</item>
            </list>
            <p>First of the first. It was the superstition of the old Romans, <hi>primam lanuginem Diis Conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crare,</hi> to consecrate the first haire of their cheeks to their gods: what was superstition in them, will bee good Religion in us, God will have our firstlings; what are they? the first borne male
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:123416:20"/> of thy Cattell, and of thy sheep, thou shalt san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie to the Lord thy God, was the old Law. But now, I will take no Bullock out of thine house, nor Goat out of thy fold: will I eate the flesh of Bulls, or drinke the blood of Goats? Offer unto mee praise, and pay thy vowes, call upon mee (but marke what followes) in the day of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, not in the night, not after Sunne set, wee must not deferre it so long: and I say, call upon him early, betime in the morning; and if not in the morning of the day, yet surely in the morning of thine age, that is, in thy youth. How many have thought to call in the evening, who have beene cald away themselves at noone, and beene benighted at mid-day? for we are here but for a time, and then must bee gone: like Travailers, or wayfaring men, wee must pay our debt and reckoning to Nature, and then away; after we have eat and drunke here, or like Tenants at will, who must give up our Title and Land, even that small portion of earth which we carry about us, when God shall call, as hee cald to <hi>Abraham, exi de terra tua,</hi> goe out of thy Land: and whither then? to the place that <hi>Iob</hi> in his tenth Chapter speaks of, darke as darknesse it selfe; where there is no order; where there is no place for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, for as the tree falleth so it lyeth. Sixe dayes shalt thou labour and doe all that thou hast to doe, in these thou must gather thy <hi>Manna;</hi> if thou gather on the seventh, it shall stinke and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:123416:21"/> bring forth wormes: never had man pardon of his sinne to whom it was not sealed in this world; we must be wrought here, and sitted and squared for the house of God, or no where, for after this life shall cease the noyse of the hammer, the Axe, and the Chisill: the day is for action, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good or ill: the night commeth, in which no man worketh; for that reason remember thy Creator here, and for this remember him here in thy youth, because it is uncertaine whether thou shalt ever be old: none are old which were not young; many are young which shall not bee old. Times and ages, God, as a wise dispenser has kept in his owne hands, to the intent that wee might suspect a shorter thred of life, and yet not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spaire of a longer.</p>
            <p>There is a time to be borne, and a time to dye (sayes <hi>Solomon</hi>) marke his language, here is birth and death, but no talke of life; as if in a new way of Philosophy, he would make a passage <hi>ab extremo, ad extremum sine medio,</hi> as if wee were to spring immediately out of our mothers wombe, out of our swadling Clouts into our winding sheet.</p>
            <p>But suppose it were so, that thou hadst a long lease of thy life, and wert forc't to go to thy grave as a sheafe of Wheat into the Barne, ripe and in a good age: suppose thou hadst a promise to see thy childrens children, and their Children, yet were it extreame impiety to deferre thy repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:123416:21"/> to thy later dayes, to give thy beautie and youth to thy pleasure, and thy wrinckles and gray haires to thy God. Hast thou not read, hath it not beene told thee, that God will have no pleasure in thy leavings, the halt, the lame, the bleare-eyed, and the blind, are these fit offerings on his Altar?</p>
            <p>Besides, how unjust is this, to play away the strength of thine age, and then to lay the burden of all thy sinnes upon thy old and decrepit age, which God knowes is a burden to it selfe, whose knees tremble and shake under as many diseases as sinnes. O Lord, that back that so stoops un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der threescore yeares, how shall it sinke under the sins of threescore yeares? the sinnes, I say, whose weight hee full well knowes, that calls to us, <hi>Come unto mee all you that are heavie laden;</hi> for this I call heaven, and earth, and hell to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse; for the earth sunk under the sins of <hi>Corah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram:</hi> the first sinne weighed the apostate Angels to hell; and now is another hell to them, and the sinne of man weighed downe from heaven to earth: The Son of God, who on the Mount of Olives sweat drops of bloud, under the load of our iniquities, and when hee bare them on the Crosse, hee cryed out in the anguish of his soule, heaven and earth beway<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the extreame weight that lay upon him, for the Sunne shut his eye, and the whole Land of <hi>Iurie</hi> became as a close mourner; for it was
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:123416:22"/> wrapt in a blacke Mantle of Darknesse from the sixt even unto the ninth houre: is this then a burthen for thine old age? for crazie and faint limbes? then let a Pigmie, a Dwarfe, twitch up Mount <hi>Aetna</hi> at the roots, and strut away with it on his shoulders.</p>
            <p>Besides all this, doe but thinke of the many and certaine miseries of that age; <hi>Nonius Marcellus</hi> coats three places out of <hi>Accius, Pacuvius,</hi> and <hi>Titinnius,</hi> where <hi>senium</hi> is put for <hi>Malum,</hi> as if it were one and the same thing to be old and miserable: adde hither the decay of Senses, conscience of an ill-acted life, the feare to dye, and yet wearinesse to live, with <hi>Chiliads,</hi> and <hi>Iliads,</hi> more of evills, Ministers to the first, I tremble to say the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond death.</p>
            <p>Beyond all this, there are some vices natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall to old age, as jealousie, peevishnesse, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rositie, loquacitie, their present life being but a vaine repetition or memorie of their former, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, they live by memorie, saies <hi>Arist.</hi> I add hither also Covetousnesse, so proper to this age, that the Philosopher therfore cals it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, uncu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, because <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, old age, and everie impotencie breeds it, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it bee, that when the gifts of body and minde faile, wee catch at those of fortune, as our last refuge, like men halfe drowned, that missing of better hold, catch at strawes or
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:123416:22"/> weeds, which reason <hi>Aquinas</hi> on that place gives; or whether it be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is the Philosophers one Reason in 2. of his <hi>Rhetor.</hi> because old men by experience best know how necessary those eternalls are, and yet how hardly got, how easily lost: This is that, that makes them, when they are even at their journies end, breake their Asses backs with saying on new provision, not much un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Rivers, that then runne biggest, and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther most waters, when they come nearest to the Sea, to their owne home.</p>
            <p>Lastly, how hardly does gray-headed sinne leave a sinner? This is that Aegyptian Tyrant, that <hi>Pharaoh</hi> that will not let Israel goe: it is continuance in sinne, that makes an earnest sinner, our first sinnes are with some reluct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ancy, some checks, some gripes, our later with delight; happy is hee that dashes those Brats, those little ones, against the Stone, as it is in <hi>Psalme</hi> one hundred thirtie sixe. Some Interpreters by little one, doe there un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand sinne in its Infancy, and by the Stone the Rock, the Corner stone, CHRIST JESUS.</p>
            <p>How hardly is the iniquity of our Heeles shooke off? <hi>Cassiodorus</hi> expounds our Heeles our later Age, and the difficultie proceeds
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:123416:23"/> partly from the Devill, to <hi>insidiaberis calcane<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> said God to the Serpent, thou shalt lye in wait for his Heele; partly from the sinner, hee is an old, a grave sinner, hardly cure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; not as if the Balme of <hi>Gilead</hi> failed, not as if GOD wanted mercie, for he ran to meet the Prodigall afarre off, and Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> saw, <hi>Ierusalem</hi> with twelve Gates open to the East three, to the West three, to the North three, and to the South three: but because God in Iustice hardens such sinners, not positively, but negatively, that is, <hi>Non impertiendo mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam, sed non impertiendo gratiam,</hi> sayes <hi>Lum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard,</hi> not by making them evill, but by not making them good, leaving them stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid, bed-ridden, and speechlesse sinners, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out sence, without motion, not able to doe or say so much as the Prodigall did, I will rise, or I would rise, and goe to my Father.</p>
            <p>Hence now I passe to the second particular, <hi>In the dayes of thy youth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why in the dayes of our youth, more than in the yeares of our youth: They that have set us out the shortest time for youth, allow us from foureteene to thirtie foure, but this is to put us in minde of uncertaintie of life, as if our youth was but for a few dayes, or like as at the end of the day comes evening, and then darke night, so at the end of our youth
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:123416:23"/> comes old Age, and then Death.</p>
            <p>Or it may bee without violence to the Text, you may take in the dayes of thy youth; for, by the good actions done in thy youth, and then the sense will bee, give testimonie that thou Remembrest thy Creator, by thy well-doing, in thy youth; for so may this word <hi>Dayes</hi> bee used: <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> (said <hi>Moses</hi>) departed full of daies, <hi>Hoc est</hi> (sayes <hi>Aquinas) plenus operibus lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis &amp; diei:</hi> Neither doe I without warrant expound this Preposition <hi>in</hi> as a causall, sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying <hi>by;</hi> so would some have it meant in the verie first word of <hi>Genesis,</hi> and so it is u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in the Psalme, <hi>In wisedome hast thou made them all:</hi> that is, <hi>by</hi> wisedome; for the Son is the wisedome of the Father: And so is it used in the first of the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, hee spake to us in his Sonne, that is, by his Son.</p>
            <p>Thus I have done with the second par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, <hi>In the dayes of thy youth.</hi> But that is not enough, the wise man addes, <hi>now in the dayes of thy youth.</hi> I say now: for now is the Sabboth Day, to the hallowing of which, GOD prefixt, as hee did to my Text, <hi>a Remember,</hi> Remember that thou keep holy the Sabboth day.</p>
            <p>Secondly, remember him now, because
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:123416:24"/> no time is thine, but this verie now, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any bee to come it is uncertaine; and what it may bring with it as uncertaine: That which is past is behinde thee, and see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thou art a Travailer on earth, the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou journyest, the further thou lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vest it.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Remember thy Creator now,</hi> because now, in this very moment, this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Article of time, does he create thy bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part, thy soule: f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r by the verie same action by which it was first created, is it till this day created, is this minute created, and shall bee created to all eternitie, (mistake mee not) the Conservation of it in being; being nothing else but the Creation of it continued: since therefore, God upholds thy soule in being by the same act, by which hee gave it being (I meane thy soule onely, for hee did not in a proper sence create thy bodie) and since no cause loseth its Name, or Formalitie, till its actuall influence, or causalitie cease: who sees not that whensoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver hee did first create it, yet he now creates it: hee is now thy Creator, therefore thou shalt now remember him: if he be thy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, thou must make him thy end: the first efficient, and the last end must needes bee co-incident: if hee doe for thee, thou
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:123416:24"/> must doe for him; if hee now remember thee, thou must not now forget him; because thou wast at first deduced from him, thou must bee thus reduced to him. <hi>Alcinous</hi> in his Introduction to <hi>Plato</hi> sayes of him, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, hee held GOD of a Sphaericall figure: and truely, though God bee of no figure, yet (to omit many instances) hee seemes to love this figure: for as a Circle returnes into it selfe, and ends where it began; so all things that were derived from him, (and what was not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from him?) must end in him: <hi>Ister, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chelous, Euphrates,</hi> and <hi>Ganges,</hi> all these Rivers flow from that mightie Well: and after all their windings, come to pay tribute, and fall with a loud noyse into that mightie Well.</p>
            <p>Last of all, Remember you especially your Creator now, because there was of late evill in your great Citie, the evill of Plague, but now is not, because the Gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant hath now laid by his Quiver, his Bow, and his Arrowes, because shee that did sit in▪ Ashes, is now become the glorie of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, the seat of joy, of mirth, and health; because now her streets, her Courts of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice, her Temples are returned from soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude to their old frequencie, because now
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:123416:25"/> shee heares not <hi>Zim,</hi> nor the Scriech-Owle by night, not the Vulture, nor the Raven by day: O let it not bee told in <hi>Edom,</hi> let not the <hi>Hittite</hi> and the Stranger heare that Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael found a mindfull God, but God an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mindfull Israel, that you are still a rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious people, though his Angel past by your houses, and your first-borne live, that you heare not him, whereas he heard for you, your verie doores cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and crying, Lord have mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy upon us.</p>
            <p>{inverted ⁂}</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>PAge 2. line 4 read <hi>vilescit</hi> for <hi>vile est.</hi> p. 3. l. 15. r. lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving for bearing p. 4. l. 17. r. mind to that, for mind that. p. 5. l. 24. r. are not ascribed, for doe not ascribe. p. 8. l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. r. put for set. p. 8. l. 16. del.?. at Arts, and set it at Sciences. p. 25. l. 16. r. carried for cursed.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:123416:25"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>